<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Novem. 24 Num. 7. The weekely newes containing these particulars. The surprising of tvvo tovvnes by the Prince of Oranges forces, and the manner of their taking, vvith the seuerall pasages of Spinolas armie lying before Breda, and our campe at Rosendale: as also the death of the Earl of Southampton and his sonne at Bergan-vp-Zomme. The taking of many places in the Grisons countrey by the French kings forces. Likewise the entertainment of many thousands of men by the State of Venice; vnder the command of Colonlel Ouentuant once one of Count Mansfields chiefe commanders. The Hollanders fortunately meeting with one of the King of Spaines plate ships comming from the West-Indies the which in a short time they ouercame and tooke: with a great victorie obtained by the Duke of Tuscans gallies, against the pirats of Argles. The disagreement which is like to happen betweene the emperour and Bethlem Gabor, and the Turke and the Emperour ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102712</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838482</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838482</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2863</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14896)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2863)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1121:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Novem. 24 Num. 7. The weekely newes containing these particulars. The surprising of tvvo tovvnes by the Prince of Oranges forces, and the manner of their taking, vvith the seuerall pasages of Spinolas armie lying before Breda, and our campe at Rosendale: as also the death of the Earl of Southampton and his sonne at Bergan-vp-Zomme. The taking of many places in the Grisons countrey by the French kings forces. Likewise the entertainment of many thousands of men by the State of Venice; vnder the command of Colonlel Ouentuant once one of Count Mansfields chiefe commanders. The Hollanders fortunately meeting with one of the King of Spaines plate ships comming from the West-Indies the which in a short time they ouercame and tooke: with a great victorie obtained by the Duke of Tuscans gallies, against the pirats of Argles. The disagreement which is like to happen betweene the emperour and Bethlem Gabor, and the Turke and the Emperour ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. I[ones] for Thomas Archer and are to be sold in Popes head Ally, ouer against the signe of the Horse-shooe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through; some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Europe --  History --  1517-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2863:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2863:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Nouem. 24. Num. 7. THE VVEEKELY Newes, containing theſe particulars. The ſurpriſing of two Townes by the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> forces, and the manner of their taking, with the ſeuerall paſages of <hi>Spinolas</hi> armie lying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Breda,</hi> and our campe at <hi>Roſendale:</hi> as alſo the death of the Earle of <hi>Southampton</hi> and his Sonne at <hi>Bergan-vp-Zoome.</hi> The taking of many places in the <hi>Griſons</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey by the <hi>French</hi> Kings forces. Likewiſe the entertainement of many thouſands of men by the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> vnder the Command of Colonell <hi>Ouentuant,</hi> once one of Count <hi>Mansfields</hi> chiefe commanders. ¶ The <hi>Hollanders</hi> fortunately meeting with one of the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> Plate Ships comming from the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> the which in a ſhort time they ouercame and tooke: with a great victorie obtained by the Duke of <hi>Tuſcans</hi> Gallies, againſt the Pirats of <hi>Argier.</hi> The diſagreement which is like to happen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Emperour and <hi>Bethlem Gabor,</hi> and the <hi>Turke</hi> and the Emperour: the receiuing of many thouſands of men, being newly diſmiſſed by <hi>Monſier Tillie,</hi> into the pay of the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by W. I. for THOMAS ARCHER, and are to be ſold in Popes head Ally, over againſt the Signe of the Horſe-Shooe. 1624.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:2863:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2863:2"/>
            <head>The Weekely Newes from <hi>Italy, Germany, France, Spaine,</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Vienna <date>the <hi>24.</hi> of October.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee vnderſtand here how that the <hi>Turkiſh Chiany</hi> who is come to the Imperiall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners which are at <hi>Commora,</hi> hath brought with him ſome hard points and Articles, which are proponuded by the <hi>Grand Signieor,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The conditions of peace which the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſodors of <hi>Bathlem Gabor</hi> hath offered vnto his Imperiall Maieſtie in the name of his Maiſter, they are likewiſe very hard and intollerable, ſo that there is little or no hope at all, that any peace or truce ſhall be concluded betwixt the Emperour, or any of them.</p>
               <p>They write out of <hi>Silecia,</hi> that the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> haue quite left both <hi>Silecia</hi> and <hi>Morauia,</hi> and that the lye vpon the frontiers of <hi>Polonia</hi> and <hi>Silecia,</hi> expecting the mercifull reſolution and pardon of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> that they may come ſafely home.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2863:3"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Vienna <date>the <hi>26.</hi> of October.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>Concerning the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> treatie of peace, wee haue yet no other tidings, but that there is come a <hi>Turkiſh Chiany</hi> (being accompanied with few perſons) to the Imperiall Commiſſioners, to ſalute and receiue them: and that he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded ſome few Articles, which the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is not to admit in any manner of wayes, although the <hi>Grand Signieur</hi> would moderate them.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Raba,</hi> that they ſtand there in feare that the <hi>Turkes</hi> will come and pillage the Countrie there about, and that they keepe ſtrong watches, and have planted their Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance vpon their walles and bulwarkes, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute them at their arriuall: as likewiſe how that there being a houſe fired by caſualtie, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants and Souldiers which are in <hi>Commora</hi> were mightilie afraid, and ſuſpected that it had beene done by the <hi>Turkes</hi> to ſurpriſe the place the better.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of this Moneth was a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation at <hi>Linty</hi> in the vpper <hi>Auſtria</hi> procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the name of the Emperour, to cite all ſuch as haue beene guiltie in the former Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, to appeare within the ſpace of ſixe weekes and three daies in the head Towne of <hi>Linty,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Emperiall Preſident and Counſell Namelie, the Count of <hi>Neggaw,</hi> Gouernour of the lower <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Hoyes</hi> Preſedent of the Counſell of the lower <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Reck,</hi> one of his Maieſties Imperiall Counſell,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2863:3"/>the Lord <hi>Heggenmiller</hi> Chanceler of the lower <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the Doctors <hi>Moſmiller,</hi> and <hi>Barthold,</hi> and to cleare themſelues. But the Preachers are authors of the Rebellion (as they write thence) are ſome 8. dayes agoe diſmiſt of their charge, and commanded to depart within the ſpace of 8. daies, which expired yeſterday: At the ſame time was not onely the preaching forbidden to the Miniſters, but alſo the ringing and ſounding of Belles to the Sextons, vpon paine of death.</p>
               <p>On the 15. of this Moneth were the Booke-ſellers Shops viewed in this Citie, and the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Proteſtant Bookes forbidden. On the ſame day arriued here the Count <hi>Nicolas Wolsky</hi> Great Marſchall of the Kingdome of <hi>Polonia,</hi> and it is rumored that he is to goe thence into the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> to the <hi>Infanta,</hi> which lieth at <hi>Bruſſell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Two daies agoe perriſhed two Barkes in the Riuer of <hi>Donaw,</hi> that were ſailing with Corne to the frontier Townes and Caſtles of <hi>Hungarie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The tidings which wee had heare lately, how that Monſieur <hi>Tilly</hi> had taken the bridge of <hi>Strasbourg</hi> is falſe, but it is ſure that he hath ſtopt the paſſages of the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> that nothing can come vp or downe without his leaue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Vienna <date>the 26. of October.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>The 19. of this Moneth departed the great Marſchall of <hi>Pelonia</hi> hence, and went as it is ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mored towards <hi>Florence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the ſame day came his Imperiall Maieſtie here backe againe from <hi>Eberſdoof,</hi> and gaue on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2863:4"/>the next Sunday after he had heard the Maſſe audience to the Ambaſſador of <hi>Bethlem Gabor;</hi> he did the like on the following Munday to the Ambaſſador of the Elector of <hi>Cullen,</hi> and graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the next Tueſday the Regalia and Fulde to the Commiſſioners of the Abbot of <hi>Fulden,</hi> which demanded them in his name. On the next Wenſday, as likewiſe yeſterday went the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour abroade to hunt the wilde Bore.</p>
               <p>Fewe dayes agoe arriued here the Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Pragne</hi> comming here poſte, and it is ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mored that the <hi>Land-graue Charles</hi> of <hi>Lichten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayn</hi> is likewiſe to come hitherwards with great ſpeede.</p>
               <p>The Count <hi>Serin Banus</hi> of <hi>Croatia,</hi> who came here likewiſe fewe dayes agoe, reporteth that he hath not onelie ſlaine many <hi>Turkes,</hi> which were pillaging the ſame Country, but that he alſo himſelfe hath made an inroade on the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Dominion, and gotten there rich booties. The <hi>Turkiſh</hi> treatie of Peace is not begunne as yet, by reaſon that the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Commiſſioners are not come together, and eſpecially ſeing that the chiefeſt of them all is yet at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Prague,</hi> that there are put in priſon three men of them which robbed the Duke of <hi>Saxon Lawenborg</hi> when he was riding towards this Citie of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This weeke was a Poſtillion or Meſſenger ſlaine, when he had taken the 9. poſt horſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Prague</hi> and <hi>Vienna,</hi> the lttters being found by a husband man, he carried them to the next
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2863:4"/>poſt, but wee cannot learne as yet in what. man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner this happenned, nor who was the author.</p>
               <p>We vnderſtand by Letters written from <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> that the Proteſtant States of <hi>Auſtria</hi> haue promiſed to pay the wages to the proteſtant Preachers which are baniſhed, for two yeares, and that they gaue to euerie one of them 1000. Rix-Dollers before their departure, and that moreouer the Proteſtant Burgurs gaue them when they tooke their leaue of them 1.2. yea. 3. Rix-Dollers, and ſome of the richer ſorts whole hand fulls of Rix-Dollers, and Duckets.</p>
               <p>They write out of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> that the Lord <hi>Boſniach</hi> hath ſurpriſed the ſmall Towne of <hi>Waith,</hi> which was in the bounds fo the <hi>Tu ke,</hi> and hauing ſlaine there 2000. <hi>Turkes,</hi> tooke moreouer 70. of them as priſoners, &amp; got there 970. <hi>Turkiſh</hi> horſe, beſides many other rich bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: Hee reſcued likewiſe all thoſe Chriſtians which the <hi>Turkes,</hi> as we mentioned heretofore had taken at <hi>Ferrels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord <hi>Eſterhaſi</hi> who is Gouernor rf <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſed,</hi> hauing ſinck fortified <hi>Ferrele,</hi> the <hi>Grand Signiour</hi> hath ſent him word, that he ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantle the place againe, ſeing it was againſt the treatie of Peace, to make any new fortifications vpon the frontiers. But he the Lord <hi>Eſterhaſi</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned this anſwere, namely, that ſeing he had ſuffered his coſin, and diuers other Chriſtians to be taken thence as priſoners, after his <hi>Trukiſh</hi> Souldiers had pillaged the place, which was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectlie againſt the treatie of Peace, he had forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2863:5"/>the fame place, that the Chriſtians might liue there ſecurle, and out of danger to be ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at the pleaſure of the <hi>Turkes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Vienna <date>the <hi>30.</hi> of October.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>The Ambaſſadors of <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> are not as yet diſpacht, nor haue vnderſtood the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours reſolution vpon their propoſitions which they haue made in the name of <hi>Bethlem Gabor.</hi> In the meane time they are dayly feaſted by ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Lords, and amongſt others the Count of <hi>Meggaw</hi> feaſted them fewe daies agoe in great Pompe and State, not ſparing any coſt vpon Players and Muſitians. It is thought that for this time (ſeing they brought ſome preſents to the Emperor) that they ſhall likewiſe be ſent home with ſome preſents.</p>
               <p>There is yet ſmall likelihood of the treatie of peace, ſeing that the <hi>Baſha</hi> of <hi>Oſsen</hi> hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelte, that hee will not ſuffer the Lord <hi>Curty</hi> the Ambaſſador of his Imperiall Maieſtie, to goe thence before the Peace be concluded. And the Emperour on the other ſide will not ſuffer this treatie to beginne, vnleſſe he the Lord <hi>Curty</hi> be at libertie; and may come to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Vienna <date>the <hi>31.</hi> of October.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>We receiued here to day tydings, how that 12000. <hi>Turkes</hi> which haue laine a while about <hi>Oſten,</hi> were marcht vp to meet againe an inrode either in <hi>Hungaria</hi> or <hi>Styria:</hi> And his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Maieſtie hath thereupon giuen order that 12000. foote ſhall with great ſpeede march to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Hungaria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2863:5"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Prague</hi> 
                     <date>the 2 of Nouember.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>Although the Emperour hath now many times giuen order, that the ſouldiers ſhould be ſent out of this Kingdome into the Empire, they will not obey his order: by reaſon of their want of payment which they expect from the Empeour, and if they continue heere any longer, we are likely to haue a generall dearth in this Kingdome; for they haue already in many places of this Kingdome conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Victualls.</p>
               <p>One who came lately from <hi>Olmits</hi> in <hi>Morauia</hi> brought heere tiding, how that the moſt part of the Coſſacks which haue layne in <hi>Seleſia,</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauia,</hi> (when they were in the pay of the Emperor) are now entered into the ſeruice of <hi>Bethlem Gabor;</hi> and many are therefore of opinion that he (<hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi>) is not to be truſted.</p>
               <p>The Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> is with 500 horſe gone to <hi>Berlin</hi> to aſſiſt there at the Chriſtning of a child of the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh.</hi> But there are ſome which hold that they are to treat there more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer of ſome matters of great importance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Siuill</hi> 
                     <date>the <hi>20.</hi> of October.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>We haue receiued tidings that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> haue taken the Admirant which is one of the Ships of our ſiluer fleete.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2863:6"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Amſterdam</hi> 
                     <date>the 9 of <hi>Nouember.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>The tyding is confirmed againe out of <hi>Spaine</hi> how that the Generall <hi>le Hermite</hi> hath taken and pillaged the Towne of <hi>Lima,</hi> and gotten there rich booties. And they write likewiſe thence that there is no hope that the ſiluer fleet ſhall this yeare come out of the Weſt-Indies, and that the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> his Factors can therefore hardly take any money vp for the ſeruice of his Maieſty.</p>
               <p>Moreouer they aduiſe vs thence that the fleete which is to be ſent againſt the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the <hi>Bay</hi> of <hi>Todos los Sanctos</hi> out of their hands, cannot ſoone be made ready for want of money, ſhips, munition, and men, although there walke dayly many Spaniſh Signiors by the ſteetes, with their feathers vpon their Hats, and threaten the <hi>Hollanders</hi> mightily.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe we vnderſtand by ſeuerall letters writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from <hi>Siuill,</hi> how that by thunder and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the golden Crowne was ſtroaken from the head of the Image or ſtatua of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> that was erected there to honour him vppon his arriuall, without doing any other hurt, ſo that there are made many ſtrange Prognoſtications, and that the rather ſeeing that the Confeſſor of the Queene, who was a very learned man, ſayd before his death, that hee was very happy to leaue this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2863:6"/>world before ſuch miſeries, as were to fall vppon <hi>Spaine</hi> happened.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Liuorno,</hi> that on the 11 of October there ariued the Arch-Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> the brother of the Emperor, who was to goe with the Gallyes of <hi>Gemia</hi> into <hi>Spaine;</hi> he was euery where very ſtately entertayned, and it is thought that he ſhall bee made Vice-Roy of <hi>Portingall,</hi> amongſt his folowers is one of the Dukes of <hi>Saxon-Weymar</hi> who is releaſed out of his impriſonment.</p>
               <p>Foure Gallyes of the great Duke of <hi>Toſcana</hi> with 3 Gallies of the <hi>Popes,</hi> and 8 Gallyes of <hi>Naples,</hi> hauing aſſaulted the Famous Pyrat of <hi>Algire, Calefare, Aller,</hi> they ſet ſo hard vpon him, that he was compelled to put the fire in his gun-pouder.</p>
               <p>But neuertheleſſe they tooke the Captaine and two other Pyrats, beſides 3 priſes of French and Low-countrymen, which they thought to carry to <hi>Algires,</hi> and ſome 150 Turkes which were vpon them are ſent to the Gallyes.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> hauing beene in <hi>Gotland</hi> and viewed his ſiluer mines, is (God be thanked) againe ſafe arriued at <hi>Coppenhugen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we vnderſtand that the moſt part of the Souldiers which the Kings of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke</hi> haue diſmiſt aſwell horſe as foote, are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in the ſeruice of the High and Mighty Lords, the States of the vnited Prouinces. The horſe are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2863:7"/>to come through the landes of <hi>Oldenborg,</hi> and <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> vnder the conduct of young Count of <hi>Thurne,</hi> and the States haue therefore ſent prouiſion in thoſe partes for them.</p>
               <p>It is rumored that the Imperial Souldiers which lye yet in <hi>Weſt-phalia,</hi> are ſpeedily to march vp, and to go to the Marquis <hi>Spinola</hi> before <hi>Breda:</hi> But ſuch as come thence, reports that they haue no minde to go to his Campe, by reaſon of the great Death and bad payment which is there made, and haue cauſed already many Souldiers to forſake it, ſo that there came dayly many of them out of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalia</hi> to ſerue the States of theſe Vnited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces.</p>
               <p>They of the Biſhoppricke of <hi>Oſnaburg</hi> haue this yeare ſlaine many Souldier of Monſieur <hi>Tilly,</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Anholt,</hi> which pillaged the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
               <p>And the Baron afore mentioned, hath thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon hauing receiued order from Monſieur <hi>Tilly,</hi> written to them of the Towne, and vrged that they ſhould receiue ſome Imperiall Souldiers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their Walles. But they haue refuſed it flatly, and are not afrayde for him.</p>
               <p>The Cardinall of <hi>Hohenſolleren</hi> would likewiſe ſine as Biſhop of <hi>Oſnaburg</hi> make his entrie in the ſame Towne.</p>
               <p>In the County of <hi>Rauenſberg,</hi> are now many Souldiers leauied for the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and are to be ſent to the ſiedge of the Marquis <hi>Spinola</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Breda.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2863:7"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Rome</hi> 
                     <date>the 29 of October.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>We haue receiued now more particular tidings from the Sea-fight that was lately betwixt 16 gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes of the Chriſtians, and 6 pyrats, in the Sea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Sardigna,</hi> not farre from the Iſle called St. <hi>Peter,</hi> for they write from <hi>Liuorno;</hi> that there were three Gallies of the Pope, eight of <hi>Naples,</hi> and fiue of <hi>Toſcanus</hi> that fight with them, and that they had two Pinaſſes, and two other great Ships with them, which they had taken from ſome Low-Country-men.</p>
               <p>And they relate how that the greateſt Ship of the Turkes, which was prouided with 50. peeces of Ordinance, and 300. men, hauing loſt her maine Maſte, through the ſhot of the Ordinance of our Gallies, the Pirates put the fire in the gun-dowder, and blew it vp, that they might not bee taken a liue: This ſhip beeing thereupon preſently ſunke, the reſt fled to ſaue themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Venice</hi> 
                     <date>the 25. of <hi>October.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>They write from <hi>Thurin</hi> that the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoy,</hi> and the Signiory of <hi>Gennu</hi> are yet both leaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng more Souldiers, and that the Duke (a fore mentioned,) granted yet lately a Patent to leauie 2000. men: As likewiſe that his Highneſſe is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2863:8"/>reſolued to purchaſe yet more lands and Lordſhips to the Marquiſate of <hi>Succarello.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the laſt Tweſday arriued here two ſhips with ſouldiers of <hi>Albania,</hi> which are to bee ſent into our Fronter Townes in <hi>Terra ferma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This weeke ſayled the two great Gallions hence being appoynted to conduct our Merchants Ships going and comming in, and from diuers ſeuerall places.</p>
               <p>The Coronells <hi>Obertront,</hi> and <hi>Schibiliſchy</hi> are here arriued, and are entred into the pay of this Signiory, which is reſolued to leauy 2000. <hi>Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes,</hi> 2000. <hi>Swiſſers,</hi> and 2000. Italian horſe.</p>
               <p>We vnderſtand by letters written from <hi>Millane</hi> how that the Gouernour of that Duke-dome hath ſent many ſouldiers without any ſound of Drum toward <hi>Come;</hi> and that the Paragor or Pay-maiſter Generall, hath furniſhed 5000. <hi>Veltoliners</hi> with armes and other neceſſaries to defend it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Letters from <hi>Emerick.</hi>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>Wee haue intelligence by letters from the town of <hi>Emrick,</hi> that the Captaine of the horſe Sirnamed <hi>Quait,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Sippenbrook</hi> hauing made paſſag into the Land of <hi>Marke,</hi> with a 100 horſe and 500 foote, which were vnder the command of <hi>Iohn Whitelme</hi> of <hi>Schorteneere,</hi> ſurpriſed and tooke the the Knight Marſhall out of the Towne of <hi>Haltin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen;</hi> where out of the walls of the Citty, he forced
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2863:8"/>him to ſhake hands and take his farwell of this life ſhooting him to death againſt a Tree: the which puniſhment his bad vſage of many of our ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers moued him to inflict vpon him.</p>
               <p>But as yet heere was not a period of their power nor an end of their conqueſt, for they proceded in the acquiring of a farther victory, laying ſiedge to the Towne of <hi>Vima:</hi> where having encamped, they ſent ſome ſhot to the Towne, as an Ambaſſador to tell them thundring in their eares, the ſcope of their approach, notwithſtanding the Towne made ſome ſmall reſiſtance; but to ſmall purpoſe: for it did but procraſtinate, not mittigate their miſery, in fine it was taken, from whence they carryed 5 peices of Ordinance, by the aſſiſtance of which they went on yet further, and they beſiedged the towne of <hi>Lunnen,</hi> and that not without as hapy ſucceſſe, as they had formerly done the other: for haueing diſcharged ſome Cannons vpon it, the towne not very well likeing of ſuch language as the Cannon noyſe, nor approouing of ſuch meſſengers as dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bullots, ſubmitted themſelues vnto them, and yeeld their perſons and their purſes, their goods &amp; themſelues into their hands, which being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht with without further delay (which allures great danger in martiall matters) they poſted let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to <hi>Emerick,</hi> the contents of which were to this effect <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That they would ſend them more ayde to the intent they might ſcoure away the ſpaniards which like ruſt hung about the countrys, and conſtrayne them to flye out of that corner.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2863:9"/>
               <p>I doubt not but this will be a <hi>Habeas corpus</hi> for <hi>Spinola,</hi> from the ſiedge of <hi>Breda:</hi> for me thinks it ſtands with reaſon that when he ſees his owne houſe on fire, he ſhould looke to the quenching of that rather then fircing of others, he ſees a certainty of loſſe in the parting with thoſe Townes, but as yet no aſſurance of gayne in the poſſeſſion of others, for hee hath not as yet attained it.</p>
               <p>But to returne to our former diſcourſe, Fame which is more ſwift then <hi>Pegaſus,</hi> certifieth the Spaniſh Commanders, which lyeth in the Town of <hi>Weſell</hi> of theſe proceeedings who immediatly, ſelected of their and the other adioyning Garriſon of <hi>Sterelen, Gelder, Rhyneberg,</hi> and marched after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with them vp into the Land of <hi>Marke,</hi> tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them, certaine number of peices of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: with an intent to make reſiſtance againſt the afore mentioned Captaine <hi>Quait,</hi> and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into battaile with him.</p>
               <p>But on the contrary ſide the States of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prouinces, together with the Counſaile of Marquis <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> ſent multituds of ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to defend and mayntaine the Townes which were ſurpriſed by them.</p>
               <p>Of late there arriued in our Campe eight companyes of <hi>Freizland,</hi> each of them being ſome 150 men ſtrong: and they had a further expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of other 8 companies which were coming out of the Biſhoppricke, and the Land of <hi>Greuinger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> hauing receiued intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of Count <hi>Manſfields</hi> approach to <hi>Seuern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergen</hi> ſent his owne Coach accompaned with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2863:9"/>foure others, 30 waggons, 2 Troopes of horſe to feth him in pompe, with no leſſe honour then magnificence.</p>
               <p>On the 4 day o this month the Count of <hi>Stirum,</hi> and the Count of <hi>Hellaine,</hi> being departed out of our Campe, and intending their courſe to <hi>Bergen vp Zoome,</hi> in the interim Count <hi>Manſfild</hi> ioyd our campe with his arriuall, hauing in his Society, the as good as old Count of <hi>Thinna</hi> the Count <hi>Ernest</hi> of <hi>Naſsaw,</hi> with many other Lordes, Commanders, and Genelemen, who rod abroad to meete, ſalute, and congratulate his comming in the name of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who receiued him with Pompe and State, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming the wellcome of ſuch a noble, vertuous, and vallient, perſonage.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> likewiſe made no long ſtay after them, but being accompaned with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Earles, Barrons, and Nobles, very Princely, and Nobley ſhewed him much countenance, and Entertayned him with much curteſie: long may they bee ſo hounoured, which haue ſo nobly fought it.</p>
               <p>Our Camp is very fortunately, and daily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richt, with multitudes of Priſoners, and prizes, taken from the Enemies: to the no leſſe aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of our ioy, then the demunition of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2863:10"/>their ſolace; for as meat doth feed the body, ſo mony doth fleſh and incourage the heart: but the moſt memorable booty that bleſt our Camp, was Lieutenant <hi>Roland Vanos,</hi> who was a Captaine of the company of their enemies foot, who was taken with ſeauen horſes, and three mules, laden with Truncks of a great Spaniſh Commanders, was carryed into <hi>Bergen vp Zoom</hi> where as yet he lyeth in the Towne.</p>
               <p>All the Trenches, Ditches, Batteryes, and Fortifications, in our Camp, are now fully fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and abſolutly compleat.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Orang</hi> likewiſe, hath recalled his ſauegards, granted to the villages, ſcituated in the <hi>Kempen:</hi> and hath alſo giuen very ſtrickt and ſtreight probition in Proclamations, or fixed Bills at <hi>Bergen vp Zoom, Seuernbergen,</hi> and other adioyning places: that they ſhall neither make ſale, or carryage of any kind of Grayne to the Camp.</p>
               <p>Through which meanes the dearth and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine in the Spaniſh Camp doth daily encreaſe; for a pound of Butter is vallued, and ſold there for ten and twelue Stiuers, a pound of Cheeſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2863:10"/>is at the ſame price, and a quart of Beere for eight pence.</p>
               <p>Moreouer they haue as little ſtore of money, as of meate ſtirring in their Army, in ſo much that men in generall haue conceiued a hope, and are ſtrongly opinionated that Marquis <hi>Spinoloa</hi> hath more will then power to continue the ſiedge of <hi>Breda;</hi> and it is thought that if not the Warres and ſpoyle done in other places, yet the hunger at home in his owne Campe, will force him to forſake the ſiedge, for if hee hath not money to get meate, nor meate to ſtay his Souldiers ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes, it is eaſie to bee coniectured that they will follow their appetites; and if hee leaue not the ſiedge, his Companies will forſake him; <hi>Et ſic famem non famam habent,</hi> they haue more hunger then honour, and report hath given vs to vnderſtand, that they haue ſtomackes like Lyons, but it is <hi>Magis ad paſſendum quam pugnandum,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to feede then to fight, but to leaue the ſiedge and to come to the beſidged.</p>
               <p>This weeke were fiue Souldiers which made an eſcape by night out of <hi>Breda,</hi> by whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation wee vnderſtood that the Towne is as yet reaſonable well prouided for victualls, and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently furniſhed with other ſuſtinance and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for it is their aſſertion that howſoeuer they bee deſtitute, and haue want of Butter, yet
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2863:11"/>they are fully furniſhed with Corne, and haue great ſtore of Cattle, aboundance of ſalt, bread, Cheeſe, Honey, Oyle, Syrrop, and other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion requiſite for the ſuſtenance and maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of this our weake and frayle life: And wee learne by particular Letters ſent <hi>Breda,</hi> that ſome three weekes ſince, there beeing a ſuruey made of the ſuſtenance, and prouiſion in the Towne, they found and vnderſtood that there was yet remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning 40000. quarters of Corne vnſpent or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toucht, which doth ſtill adde to the former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of <hi>Spinolaes</hi> relinquiching the ſiedge, for if the Towne bee ſo well furniſhed with men, meate, and munition, it is probable that <hi>Spinola</hi> being ſo defectiue in purſe and prouiſion doth but <hi>littus arare,</hi> as they ſay, or <hi>Aethiopem lauare,</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in vaine, as the ſowing on the ſhore, or the waſhing of a Blackamore; but to leaue this to the cenſure of ſound iudgements, I proceede in my diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Count Henry</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> hath lately likewiſe fully finiſhed all his Quarters, with all the workes appertayning and belonging to them: Hee hath alſo prouided, and taken order that none of our victualls or any other of our adherents ſhall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port or carry any ſuſtinance to any of our enemies or foes forces.</p>
               <p>Count <hi>Manſfield</hi> and the old Count of <hi>Thieru</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2863:11"/>hauing had long conference, and large conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with his Excellence, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> tooke their leaue and farewell of him, who as fame tells vs, are after the expiration of a ſmall time, are to meete the Engliſh at the places by them appoynted, although from vs concealed, and heere of late haue beene great ſummes of money gathered, and ſent ouer into theſe prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces out of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither is it buryed in concealement, that the <hi>French</hi> King hath receiued into his pay 2800 Horſe, the which haue formerly ſerued <hi>Mounſier Tilly,</hi> who became humble and carneſt ſuitors to ſerue vnder Count <hi>Manſfield,</hi> and there are yet expected 1000 Horſe more which will come to offer their ſeruice very ſpeedely, and to enter into the pay of the King of <hi>France,</hi> who is ſtill encreaſing his Forces, whoſe power as it is not yet in the full, ſo yet it is not in the Wayne: For euery day there bee more addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to it.</p>
               <p>We haue likewiſe intelligence, and vnderſtand further more by letters, that the Conſtable <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiare</hi> hath with no leſſe ſpeed then ſucceſſe ariued amongſt the Griſons, for he is not onely already there, but he hath ſubiected to the yoake of his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience many places and paſſages, the which hee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2863:12"/>hath effected, wrought and brought to paſſe, as well by his owne proper forces as by the aſſiſtance of the Duke of Sauoy, moreouer the French king hath ſent ouer alſo three regiments to ayde him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Bergen vp Zoame.</hi>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>Our eares of late haue beene the wofull obiects of vnſortunate news from <hi>Bargaine vp Zoame,</hi> viz. that the Earle of <hi>Southampton</hi> falling ſick, according to ſomes falſe relation, of the plague, but according to truth, of the bloudy fluxe at <hi>Roſcindale,</hi> from whence he was carried to the Towne of <hi>Bergen vp Zoame,</hi> where his ſoule forſooke that earthly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion place, and departed out of this wretched world: but as who ſhould ſay, death had an intent to make a ſecond part of our ſorrow, with his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall axe he cut downe both tree and fruit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for the Earle of <hi>Southamptons</hi> hopefull ſonne followed his father in the ſhadie paths of death, who had alſo in the ſame place, and at the ſame time a period impoſed vnto his life.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2863:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
